Guide to the James Dunn papers, 1966-1990.
Dunn, James papers, 1966-1990.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
James Dunn papers, 1966-1990.
27-2-3170.
James A. Dunn.
7 cubic ft.
Correspondence, articles, manuscripts, manuals, photographs, film reels, reports, educational materials, notes, theses.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
Materials concerning the American Institutes for Research, education norms, vocational education, educational psychology and Dunn's career in the Education Department at Cornell University.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Education, Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, articles, manuals, guides, course material, photographs and movies concerning the American Institutes for Research, education norms, vocational education, educational psychology and Dunn's career in the Education Department at Cornell University.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Dunn, James A.; American Institutes for Research.; Cornell University--Students.; Cornell University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Education--Study and teaching.; Educational psychology--study and teaching.; Vocational education--United States.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. American Institutes for Research (AIR), 1968-1977)
Boxes 1-2
Series II. OST, 1966-1979
Boxes 3-4
Series III. YETP: Basic Skills, 1980-1990
Box 3 Folder 8
Box 4 Folders 32-36
Boxes 5-7
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. American Institutes for Research (AIR), 1968-1977
  - Project Plan
    - AIR - Occupations (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - AIR- Guidance program in the plan system of individualized education (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - AIR- Contacts, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AIR- Evaluation project
    - Project Plan (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Plan Guidance Flow Chart (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AIR- VECS and CCEM
    - AIR VECS II, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - CCEM- Monograph notebook (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - CCEM- Publisher contacts (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AIR- DS Project Descriptions
    - CE curriculum materials guide (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Monograph III (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - CCEM Monograph (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Project Descriptions (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AIR- Salary Chronology
    - Old AIR salary schedules (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Salary chronology (Box 1, Folder 14, 16)
    - Recent AIR correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - AIR- Benefits
    - Personnel Reviews- JAD (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - AIR- Other Files
    - AIR- Employees' Handbook (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Annual Report, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - AIR Corporate (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - AIR Phone Directory, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - AIR- Greenbriar 71
    - AIR Directors' Meeting- Greenbriar, Jan. 1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - AIR- La Costa 74
    - Report to the Board of Directors- American Institutes for Research, Aug. 17-19, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - La Costa, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Report to the Board of Directors, American Institutes for Research, Feb. 14-16, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Report to the Board of Directors, American Institutes for Research in the Behavioral Sciences, Feb. 5-8, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Project Record - American Institutes of Research Developmental Systems Group (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Report to the Board of Directors, American Institutes for Research in the Behavioral Sciences, Aug. 20-23, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - JAD/WVS Memos: Personnel Policies (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Chronological File, Nov. 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - WVC Chronological file (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Summary of Problems with WVC (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Personal Problems with WVC (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "For discussion with Bill Clemans" (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Contracts (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Copyright Agreement (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Suggested Agreement Formats (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Preliminary Drafts- publishing agreement (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Draft Revisions- Plan Guidance Modules (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Plan Guidance Modules (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - DS Brochures and Promo Materials
    - DS Brochures (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - DS Promo Materials (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - DS Promo Materials (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - AIR Promotion Materials
    - AIR Promotion Materials (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Program Promotion Plan (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Sponsor Contact Form (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - DS Administrative Guide (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Cost of Living- AIR growth (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series II. OST, 1966-1979
  - Manuals
    - The OST: Theory, Instrument and Norms, by James Dunn, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - On Science and Theory, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Psychology and Assumptions Regarding the Nature of Man, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Matrix Theory of Cognitive Structure, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - III. Early Cognitive Theory: The Associationists, Mar. 17, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - IV. Guilford and the Structuralists, Mar. 17, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - V. Kelly and the Constructionists, June 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - OST Instrumentation (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Manuscripts
    - Sample Materials to Practice OST Scoring (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - VII. "Cognitive Style & Its Impact on Cognitive Performance", 1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "Concept Formation, Cognitive Structures & Technology Transfer", 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - OST Literature (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - OST Manuscript, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "Characteristic Patterns of High and Low Performance Rated Counselor-Candidates," thesis by Robert Innis Havens, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Exemplary Student Papers (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "The Object-Sorting Task Project Type: Structured Divergent Versus Normal Divergent" by Karoline A. Fuata'l, Spring 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "A Comparative Study of Chinese and American Performance.. ." - by J.A. Dunn, Zhang Xiao-yan, & R.E. Ripple, Nov. 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "A Comparative Study of Chinese and American Thinking Styles in Divergent and Convergent Thinking Tasks"- a thesis by Zhang Xiao-Yan, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "On Concept Formation, Recognition and Utilization: A Method for the Study of Cognitive Operations" by James Dunn (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Three theses by Ronald Curcio, Philip Lane Safford & Barbara Lorraine Fisher Landau (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Concept Formation, Recognition & Utilization", 1986 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Papers (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Lazarus Khabanyane, Education 711, July 1986 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Laura Bloomberg, Education 711, May 5, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Hansen, Zona Scheiner, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Concept Formation
    - Livonia Study (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Progress Reports (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - OST Graphs (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous Charts and Graphs (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Block Specifications (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Chapter IV Instrumentation (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - OST Descriptors (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - OST Intro (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous Materials (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Patterns of Intellectual Development" (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "Request for Macintosh Programming Assistance" (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Concept Formation, Cognitive Structures and Technology Transfer" (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - OST Photographs
    - Null Left (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Null Right (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Angular (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Short (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Tall (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - OST Photos to do (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Test Strips (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous photographs for testing purposes (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Miscellaneous photograph materials (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Negatives (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - OST photo book (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - OST- master photo set (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Other OST
    - OST Results (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - OST Monograph Part II- Results (original) (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Data Coding and Analysis
    - Instrumentation (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "School Management" (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous Charts and Graphs (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Basic Skills Problem
    - Introduction to the Basic Skills Problem (clear overheads) (Box 4, Folder 11, 14)
    - Sample Letters, State and Local Norms: Basic Skills in Vocational Education (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Basic Skills through Vocational Education- overview and development (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Basic Skills Project (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Basic Skills Materials Development (overheads) (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Basic Skills Materials Revision and Final Product Production (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous Basic Skills Materials (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - New York State Norms, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - New York State Norms, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Utah Norms, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Maryland Norms, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Program Difference, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - CIOE
    - Reporting Student Progress, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Managing Student Progress, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Student Program Planning Information (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Prescriptive Teaching (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Washington D.C. Basic Competency, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - AVEA attitudes survey, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - AVEA-CIOE (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Test Results (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Series III. YETP: Basic Skills, 1980-1990
  - YETP Curriculum Guide (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Basic Skills- annual report, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Teaching Basic Skills through Vocational Education (introductory guide), Sept. 1980 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Business Proposals, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Basic Skills Technical Assistance Requests (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Teaching Oral Communication Skills in Vocational Education, Sept. 1980 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Resource Guide, Teaching Basic Skills through Vocational Education, Sept. 1980 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Talks and Workshops
    - Cincinnati Consultation, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - New Jersey Talk, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Maryland Workshop, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Ohio State Conference, Feb. 1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ohio State-CVTE visit (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Career Education National Forum held in Columbus, Ohio, Mar. 19-21, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - University of Nevada in Las Vegas Conference, May 1982 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Utah State Conference, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Speech notes from Sandy, Utah, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Basic Skills Workshop in Sacramento, California, Mar. 1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Basic Skills Symposium, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Basic Skills Workshop held in Cheverly, Maryland, Apr. 1982 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Basic Skills Workshop held in Seattle, Washington, Mar. 22, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Basic Skills Workshop held in Chicago, Illinois, Jan. 1982 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Basic Skills Workshop held in Atlanta, Georgia, Dec. 1981 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - "A Vocational Education Mathematics Curriculum"- Cincinnati Public Schools, Dec. 12, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Basic Skills Workshop held in Chicopee, Massachusetts, Nov. 23-24, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Conference in theWestern Curriculum Coordination Center in Koror, Palau, Sept. 27- Oct. 1, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Arithmetic Norms for Vermont and New York States, 1983 & 1986 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Example Survey of Basic Skills (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Essex Junction Pre/Post Arithmetic (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Cornell Test of Basic Skills: Basic Skills Overhead Presentation (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - New York State Norms
    - Keys- Math (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Keys-Reading (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Test Key (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Keys- Arithmetic (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Guide to Vocational Education Materials and Practices (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - New York State Norms (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Vermont Norms
    - Vermont Test Scores (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Outcomes of Occupational Education- Instrumentation Report (draft), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Outcomes of Occupational Education- Instrumentation Report, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - "Systematic Error Analysis as an Empirical Basis for Analytic Teaching", Dec. 13, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Basic Skills Report (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Basic Skills Guides
    - Teacher Guide- Teaching Basic Skills through Vocational Education (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - "Basic Skill Development Through Vocational Education" - Business Proposal, June 21, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - "Literature Search,"Teaching Basic Skills through Vocational Education, Apr. 1989 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - "Field Test Plan and Site Selection,"Teaching Basic Skills through Vocational Education, Apr. 1980 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Teaching Oral Communications Skills in Vocational Education, Oct. 1980 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Teaching Basic Skills through Vocational Education, Oct. 1980 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Teaching Reading Skills in Vocational Education, Oct. 1980 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Teaching Writing Skills in Vocational Education, Oct. 1980 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Teaching Mathematical Skills in Vocational Equation, Oct. 1980 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Teaching Basic Skills through Home Economics, Sept. 1981 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - "Sample Lesson Ideas for Basic Skill Instruction in Selected Vocational Programs," Teaching Basic Skills through Vocational Education, Apr. 1982 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - "Selected Instructional Materials for Teaching Basic Skills in Vocational Education," Teaching Basic Skills through Vocational Education, Apr. 1982 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - "Readability Analyses of Selected Vocational Texts," Teaching Basic Skills through Vocational Education, Apr. 1982 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Basic Skills Miscellaneous Materials (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Proposal for an external degree program leading to the Degree of Master of Arts with a major in Vocational Education, May 1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Evaluation Report, External Degree Programs, 1976-77 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - CCEM Interim Reports, Dec. 1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Field Test and Revision of 88 Career Education Curriculum Units, May 9, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Design and Packaging of Impact Evaluation Models for Peace Corps Programs- Part I, Sept. 20, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - Basic Skills Development through Vocational Education- annual report, 1980-81 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - State Dissemination Plan for Vocational Education Instructional Materials- Business Proposal, July 16, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - State Dissemination Plan for Vocational Education Instructional Materials- Technical Proposal, July 16, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - TV-CAP Career Awareness Programs for Children- Part I, Jan. 30, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
    - Miscellaneous Basic Skills materials (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Request for Proposal- Field Testing Vocational Education Curriculum Specialist Materials, Aug. 21, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Request for Proposal- Basic Skill Development Through Vocational Education, June 21, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - "Freestyle Follow-up" found in American Education, Dec. 1980 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Basic Skill Development through Vocational Education - Technical Proposal, June 21, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Basic Skill Development through Vocational Education - Technical Proposal with best and final addendum, Sept. 18, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Identification of Evaluated, Exemplary Activities in Career Education (K-12), May 12, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module P-7-1-G (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module E-6-1-G (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module E-7-1-G (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module E-7-2-G (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module E-7-3-G (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module E-8-1-G (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-3-1-G (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-6-1-G (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-6-3-G (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-7-1-G (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-7-2-G (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-7-3-G (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-8-1-G (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module S-6-2-G (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module S-7-1-G (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module S-7-2-G (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module S-7-4-G (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module S-8-1-G (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module S-8-2-G (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module S-2-1-G (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-5-1-G (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-5-2-G (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-5-4-G (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-5-5-G (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-5-7-G (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-5-8-G (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module M-5-9-G (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module P-5-9-G (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module P-5-10-G (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module P-5-10-G (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Building Your Tomorrows- Module P-5-11-G (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Module List and Descriptions (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - AIR Proposal Writing (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - CCEM Monthly & Quarterly Progress Reports (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - AIR- "Publisher Procurement for Educational Products" by James Dunn, June 1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - AIR-"Toward More Natural Field Testing of Classroom Materials" by Dewey Lipe & Jacqueline E. Haveman, June 1977 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - AIR-"Career Education Curriculum Materials Guide" by Carol B. Kaplan, June 1977 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Field Test Report on 130 Career Education Modules- Parts II-IV, Dec. 1976 (Box 7, Folder 6-8)
    - Basic Skills Worksheet (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Career Education Curriculum Development: Grades K-9, Oct. 1974 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Course 311
    - Education 311 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Education 311 - lecture notes (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Education 311 - master review (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Scholar's Soliloquy (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Education 311 - overhead slides, Jan. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Education Courses
    - Education 610 - Course Syllabus, Fall 1987 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Education 711 - Course Description, Spring 1988 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Education 612 - Course Announcement & Topic Outline, Spring 1985 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Education 612 - Reading List, Spring 1985 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Education 310 - course description, Fall 1989 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Current Criticism (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Education 212 - Readings (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - "On Schools and Schooling: Lessons From a Review of the History of American Education" written by James A. Dunn (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Psychopathology (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - POW (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Conflict and Stress (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Developmental Psychology- Readings, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Educational Psychology, Summer 1969 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Readings for Educational Psychology-Education 311
    - "The Social Psychology of Instruction" (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - "Developmental Psychology", Jan. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - "Intelligence and Creativity", Jan. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - "Testing and Assessment", July 1989 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - "Learning", July 1989 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - "Cognitive Psychology", July 1, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - "Instructional Psychology", Jan. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - "Research and Research Methods", July 1, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - "Thinking and Cognition", Jan. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - "Perception", Jan. 1990 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Reels
    - The Evolution of Clinical Psychology, Molly Harrower (Reel 1)
    - Projective use of the Wechsler, Bellevue (Reel 1)
    - Measurement of Abilities, Ann Anastasi (Reel 2)
    - The Development of Clinical Psychology, Lawrence E. Abt (Reel 3)
    - Clinical and Developmental Aspects of Child Psychology, Charlotte Buhler (Reel 3)
    - Perception and Reading, J. Bergan (Reel 4)